A Guide to the George Washington National Forest Oral Histories, 1994: SdArch 6
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
George Washington National Forest Oral Histories
1994
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Pisciotta, Dominic
SdArch 6
247
.2 cubic feet; 3 folders, 6 audiocassettes, 8 cds
The George Washington National Forest Oral History Collection, 1994, is comprised of audio recordings and transcripts documenting interviews conducted by a JMU student intern with Jacob Kagey and Earnest Dickerman, employees of George Washington National Forest National Park, on the topics of botanical and wilderness history.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Dominic Pisciotta, March 7, 1995.
Bio/Historical Note
Dominic Pisciotta was a senior at James Madison University, conducted these interviews in fulfillment of a JMU student internship, during the fall of 1994. The project was funded in part by the U.S. Forest Service.
Scope and Content
George Washington National Forest Oral Histories, 1994, is comprised of audio recordings and transcripts documenting interviews conducted by a JMU student intern with Jacob Kagey and Earnest Dickerman, employees of George Washington National Forest National Park, on the topics of botanical and wilderness history.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Forest reserves -- George Washington National Forest (Va. and W. Va.); Forest management -- George Washington National Forest (Va. and W. Va.); Wildlife management -- George Washington National Forest (Va. and W. Va.); Botany -- George Washington National Forest (Va. and W. Va.); Zoology -- George Washington National Forest (Va. and W. Va.); Biodiversity conservation; Wildlife conservationists -- Virginia; National parks and reserves -- Virginia; Wilderness Society (U.S.); Wilderness Society; United States. Wilderness Act; Sierra Club; Trees -- Diseases and pests
- 6-1: Oral History Project proposal, Pisciotta, September 14, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Background research paper describing the purpose of the oral history project on "the diverse biology of the George Washington National Forest and the efforts to preserve... [its] forest and wilderness areas." Also includes historical perspective on "The American wilderness movement" and "A biological synopsis of the George Washington National Forest."
- 6-2: Jacob Kagey interviewed by Dominic Pisciotta, September 16, 22, 1994
  These interviews record the recollections of Mr. Jacob Kagey, retired cabinetmaker and naturalist/flora expert, one of two individuals interviewed for an oral history project, the purpose of which was to "make an historical record of the diverse biology of the George Washington National Forest and the efforts to preserve... [its] forest and wilderness areas." Records Mr. Kagey's interests and vast knowledge of George Washington National Forest flora including information, some previously undocumented, on native, prolific and rare plants: Mentions early interest in trees and flowers, hiking partners and the Appalachian Trail Club. Describes in detail various flora and their locations in the area, primarily in Rockingham and Augusta Counties. Specifically mentions various species of orchids, ferns, lady slippers, trillium, shale barren plants, star flowers and oak trees. Talks about approach to finding plants, contacts with other local experts/botanists and discoveries which have been recorded in "The atlas of the Virginia flora." Mentions invasive plants and other environmental factors impacting flora. Recorded at the home of Mr. Jacob Kagey of Bridgewater, Va. on Sept. 16 and Sept. 22, 1994.
  - Transcript and Supplemental Documents, September 16, 22, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Original audiocassette, 1994 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA006-CS-001)
  - Original audiocassette, 1994 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA006-CS-002)
  - Original audiocassette, 1994 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA006-CS-004)
  - Preservation master (Box 1, Cd SA006-OP-001)
  - Preservation master (Box 1, Cd SA006-OP-002)
  - Preservation master (Box 1, Cd SA006-OP-003)
- 6-3: Earnest Dickerman interviewed by Dominic Pisciotta, October 11, 19, 1994
  These interviews record the recollections of Mr. Ernest M. Dickerman, retired wildlife conservationist and lobbyist for the Wilderness Society. One of two individuals interviewed for an oral history project, the purpose of which was to "make an historical record of the diverse biology of the George Washington National Forest and the efforts to preserve... [its] forest and wilderness areas." Records Mr. Dickerman's interests and knowledge of the American wilderness movement and efforts to secure wilderness areas throughout the Eastern United States. Includes information about the founding of the Wilderness Society, details concerning the Wilderness Act of 1964 and the National Wilderness Preservation System, along with many facts surrounding Eastern wilderness areas. Provides insight into his job while a lobbyist in Congress; travels to inform and gain support; testifying at hearings; and relations with various land management agencies. Relates early histories and conflicts with timber and mining industries; the Sierra Club; and the U.S. Forest Service.
  - Transcript and Supplemental Documents, October 11, 19, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Original audiocassette, 1994 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA006-CS-003)
  - Original audiocassette, 1994 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA006-CS-005)
  - Original audiocassette, 1994 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA006-CS-006)
  - Preservation master (Box 1, Cd SA006-OP-004)
  - Preservation master (Box 1, Cd SA006-OP-005)
  - Preservation master (Box 1, Cd SA006-OP-006)
  - Preservation master (Box 1, Cd SA006-OP-007)
  - Preservation master (Box 1, Cd SA006-OP-008)